ROLES

State of Iowa IT Oversight Management Team Member for ELIAS (DHS) & MIDAS (MMIS – [IME]) State of Iowa ELIAS PMO & IT Project Manager Project Manager, Org. Change/Communications Sales Manager

Customer Service & Assistant Manager (Banking) Human Resources (HR) Project Mgt./Mgt. Training Program & Project Management

Exec. Steering Comm. Chair - Program/Project Mgt.

Team Leadership

Member of Self-Managed HR Training Team Software Trainer

Over Day (Charles

Org. Dev./Strategic/Tactical Planning

Budget Management

Knowledge Transfer/Instructional design

Fundraiser

Marketing

TOOLS/METHODS

PMBOK/BABOK

Life Cycle Project Management/Software Development Life Cycle (SDLC)

Negotiation

Continuous Process Improvement (CQI)

Change - Kotter/Prosci/ADKAR

Adult Learning Theory/ADDIE Instructional Design

Coaching/Executive Coaching

MS Office/MS Project/LMS/SharePoint

PowerPoint/CorelDraw/Graphic Design

INDUSTRY APPLICATION

Information Technology
Government/Medicaid/ACA
Human Services/Healthcare/Insurance
Corporate/Manufacturing/Energy/Retail
Law Enforcement/Corrections

EDUCATION

BS, cum laude, Sociology 4 years Education Major

Financial/Mortgage/Banking

ADDITIONAL TRAINING

Human Resource Leadership Education Zenger Miller Team Facilitation/ USDL Labor-Mgt. Relations

HIT & MMIS Introduction

MS Project – Wells Fargo

Project Management - Josine & Assoc

PMBOK (PMP) Learn Smart Mastery Cert. - Proj.

Mgt. Overview

ITIL Foundations Introduction

Flawless Consulting Skills

SAP/ERP, HCM (HR), & ABAP Introduction Agile and Scrum Methodology Fundamentals

CQI (synonymous with LEAN/Six Sigma)

Page 1 of 5

Confidential

EXPERIENCE SUMMARY

I have developed a reputation as an energized, collaborative, and focused program and project manager capable of flexing with frequently changing landscape, who has a balanced mix of technical expertise, human resource management, project leadership, organizational change management, and interpersonal skills needed to solve complex issues.

Providing program, project management, and oversight over large-scale, top-priority initiatives, I have driven the high-quality completion of multiplex, enterprise wide, programs and projects for the:

- State of Iowa Department of Human Services (DHS) ELIAS
 Project (An Information Technology [IT] application system to
 determine eligibility for Medicaid, CHIP, and other public
 assistance programs.);
- Iowa Medicaid Enterprise MIDAS IT Project (The development and implementation of a new Medicare Management Information System (MMIS), and Pharmacy Point-of-Sale system [POS]).
- Wells Fargo Home and Consumer Finance Group, F500; and
- State of Iowa Department of Administrative Services.

CORE QUALIFICATIONS

- Adept at initiating, planning, executing, monitoring, controlling, and closing a project.
- Experienced in creating attainable objectives, developing requirements, deliverables, and managing the triple constraint (Time, scope, and cost).
- Proven ability to lead globally diverse cross functional teams across broad technical, financial, and business disciplines, focusing them on business objectives and tracked progress to ensure project milestones are completed on time, on budget, and with the desired results.
- Background in software, employment law, human resource management, team building, and performance management.
- Compelling professional speaker and facilitator.
- Experience in managing/monitoring multiple concurrent work streams.
- Robust client/stakeholder management and communication skills - Flawless Consulting ©, resistance management, and customer relations.
- Specialized forte in **effective communication**, **collaborative leadership**, and conflict resolution.
- Consistent monitoring and **mitigation of risk** factors.
- Continuous Quality Improvement practitioner.
- Creative expository and technical writing abilities, including project planning, status reports, proposal development, and written statements of work.
- Able to move between Agile and Waterfall approaches creating detailed project road maps, plans, schedules, and work breakdown structures (WBS). Scrum fundamentals.
- Business Process Redesign/Reengineering Co-creation and documentation of business processes and work flows; and participation in requirement gathering and identification of tasks for automation.



CHRONOLOGICAL SUMMARY OF EXPERIENCE

Rising Phoenix Consulting – Role: IT Project Manager, Organizational Change/Communication Leader, and Software Consultant (01/2007 to present)

- State of Nebraska Medicaid, IBM Cúram Project Role: Project Manager, Org. Change (12/2016 06/2017)
 - Initiated, planned, and executed project strategies for large scale statewide departmental change.
 - Extensive project interaction with designers, developers, subject matter experts (SME's), and product owners.
 - Multiple deliverables:
 - Supported the SDLC, participating in and documenting functional design reviews, and user case meetings, conducting Change Impact Assessment (CIA) meetings, and attending IBM Cúram Sandbox training.
 - o Business Process Redesign/Reengineering Participation in and documentation of requirement gathering and identification of tasks for automation.
 - o Researched, developed, and wrote technical State Medicaid Change Impact Assessments (CIA) comparing current processes with changes brought by new software to define new processes.
 - o Defined and wrote proposed action steps to address gaps and assist with State decision-making.
 - Conducted ongoing risk identification and mitigation.
- American Enterprise Group (Insurance) Role: Project Manager, Org. Change (09/2015-12/2015)
 - CQI
 - Initiated, planned, executed, and monitored/controlled project/deliverables.
 - Reported to the Chief Information Officer and had senior leadership interactions and presentations.
 - Multiple project deliverables:
 - o Designed, developed, and delivered training for leadership and staff.
 - Provided a systems audit.
 - o Identified gaps.
 - o Proposed and implemented solutions.
- State of Iowa State IT Oversight Management Team for the multimillion dollar, high risk, multifaceted Eligibility Integrated Application Solution Project (ELIAS), and on the State IT Oversight Management Team for Medicaid Integrated Data Administration Solution Project (MIDAS), (The development and implementation of a new Medicare Management Information System [MMIS], and Pharmacy Point-of-Sale system [POS]), Iowa Medicaid Enterprise (IME). Role: State Oversight Team Project Manager, Organizational Change/Communication (06/2013-12/2014)
 - Reported directly to the State's executive sponsor and IT project director.
 - Provided project oversight of all implementation and transition activities associated with the project including monitoring resources, budget, time, cost, scope, risk management, quality assurance, testing, technical system integration, certification, communication, and training as a member of the State IT Oversight Management Team.
 - Team oversight responsibility for 125 globally diverse contractors, and DHS employees, monitoring multiple concurrent work streams including application development, training, change, business analysis, etc.
 - Project Manager, Project Management Office (PMO) team.
 - Initiated, planned, and executed project management strategies to address change and communication.
 - Monitored impacts for State of Iowa citizens/customers.
 - Defined, monitored, and managed project risks.
 - Business Process Redesign/Reengineering Co-creation and documentation of new PMO business processes and work flows.
 - Initiated, planned, executed, and monitored a high-profile audit.
 - Used executive coaching to create leadership alignment.
 - Designed, developed, and delivered training for leadership and staff to create behavioral change, increase awareness, and adopt an organizational restructure.

Rising Phoenix Consulting – Role: IT Project Manager, Organizational Change/Communication Leader, and Software Consultant (01/2007 to present) continued

- Created, maintained, and standardized business practices and interventions that reduced costs and effectively managed resources within ELIAS, a Waterfall/Agile environment entangled in the complexity of federal and state government contracts, regulations, politics, and deliverables; Affordable Care Act and Medicaid; multiple vendors; multiple project managers; State teams; and competing interests.
- Interacted with other project leaders, product owners, Scrum teams, Agile coaches, and the source integrator (SI) to translate and communicate user needs and IT information, support the SDLC, production efforts, business process planning, and build a collaborative cohesive production environment.
- Provided a structured organizational change strategy based on Prosci and Kotter methodologies, and developed assessments, and education.
- Integrated collaborative leadership, conflict resolution, CQI/Lean strategies and skill sets, within ELIAS, a Waterfall/Agile environment entangled in the complexity of federal and state government contracts, regulations, politics, and deliverables; Affordable Care Act and Medicaid; multiple vendors; multiple project managers; State teams; and competing interests.
- With cross-divisional planning and coordination, wrote internal and external communications for the ELIAS project including articles, newsletters, emails, reports, proposals, and high profile letters to clients, field staff, and executives.
- Partnered with the Governor's Chief Information Officer and Iowa Department of Human Services executive leadership on high profile communications.
- Measured business readiness and stakeholder engagement.
- Artifact collection and reporting SharePoint.
- East Coast utility company (Proprietary) Role: SAP ERP Functional Consultant (11/2012 02/2013)
 - **Provided technical support** for a large scale (25,000+ Staff), East Coast, multiple location, SAP ERP Mobile conversion project.
 - Worked through system defects.
 - Served as a liaison between End Users and Technical Support staff.
- United States International Financial Brokerage (Proprietary) Role: Proprietary Software Functional Consultant (03-2012 - 10/2012)
 - Provided expertise and support as part of a large scale (15,000+ Advisors), nationwide, multiple location, IT system conversion project.
 - Multiple deliverables:
 - Worked through system defects.
 - Researched, customized, and provided system education for field staff.
 - o Served as a liaison between End Users and Technical Support staff.

Wells Fargo Home and Consumer Finance Group - Role: Program/Project Management - Inclusion (03/2000 – 01/2007)

- During a large scale corporate merger affecting 260,000+ employees, I was sought out for my proficiency in project management, change management, HR, education, and inclusive practices to co-create a strategic master plan, and lead the integration of global inclusion strategies in the organizational culture of a Wells Fargo acquisition.
- Program/project management, leading the change in acquisition culture, and serving on the Human Resources Team. This included multiple parallel diversity education related projects, enterprise wide strategic planning, and community outreach projects. It involved governance/oversight; planning and administering projects; financial management; technology; and other factors in the environment supporting inclusion efforts; and multi-level planning.
 - o Accountable to executive sponsors for schedule, budget, and quality of program components.
 - o Reviewed project plans to ensure they fit our overall inclusion strategy, plan, and schedule.
 - Escalated decisions to executive sponsors and leadership as necessary.

Wells Fargo Home and Consumer Finance Group - Role: Program/Project Management - Inclusion (03/2000-01/2007) continued

- o Introduced metrics to measure success, including Return on Investment.
- o Learning Management System (LMS) experience.
- Led globally diverse, cross-functional teams, across all business lines and levels, in strategic program planning, stakeholder analysis, and schedule development to infuse change in multiplex systems including:
 - Educational curriculum
 - Marketing
 - Contracting services with minority/women-owned businesses
 - Emerging markets
 - Recruitment and retention
- Partnered with HR generalists, employee relations, communications, recruitment, and learning and development teams.
- Project management responsibilities. Initiated, planned, executed, monitored/controlled, and closed projects. Wrote statements of work, identified scope, defined risks, established work breakdown structures, and timelines. Monitored and controlled budget, time, and costs.
- Vendor oversight.
- Business Process Redesign/Reengineering documented business processes and workflows. Created, maintained, and standardized business practices and interventions.
- Online technology Designed, wrote, and delivered on-line legally-based programming, taught Webinars, and coordinated the requirements gathering and analysis for on-line COTS software.
- Chair of Executive Steering Committee for State of Iowa's Diversity Conference. Leadership, resource oversight, program and project management responsibility, community outreach, and communications.

Envision Seminars - Role: Project Management, Organizational Transformation (04/1995 - 03/2000)

- Human capital development, linking education to organizational goals, objectives, and strategies.
- Taught leadership/management/ human resource/compliance curriculum.
- Met client needs through consulting, project management, negotiation, assessment, instructional design, and project delivery.
- Project manager. Led the process of analyzing human systems, and developed, implemented, and evaluated solutions.
- Certified software educator for Executrain (a computer/software training company).
- Project management responsibilities for a *Reverse Mentoring* senior leader succession program for a global energy leader. Initiated, planned, executed, monitored/controlled, and closed the project.

State of Iowa, Department of Administrative Services (Human Resources) - Role: Project Manager, Leadership Training (09/1988 – 04/1995)

- Co-managed the State of Iowa Human Resources Training Department as part of a self-directed work team.
- Oversight responsibilities for a \$500K training budget.
- Forecasted budgetary needs to meet the demands of human capital development.
- Conducted needs assessments to identify training needs.
- Learning Management System (LMS).
- Multiple project management responsibilities:
 - Request for Proposal process including assessment tool development, evaluation, and negotiation.
 - o Vendor solicitation, management, and negotiation.
 - o Governor's Applied Management Series certification completion program for leaders.
- Human capital development, linking education to the state's goals, objectives, and strategies.
- Business Analysis Facilitation of business processes and modeling; and requirements gathering.

State of Iowa, Department of Administrative Services (Human Resources) - Role: Project Manager, Training (09/1988 - 04/1995) continued

- Drove organizational transformation through leadership/management human resource/compliance curriculum. (List upon request.)
- Worked with all state medical facilities, Corrections, Law Enforcement, DHS, and other state departments.
- Conducted recruitment interviews and hired qualified trainers. Wrote performance evaluations.
- Certified in Zenger Miller Team Facilitation and Continuous Quality Improvement Training.
- Completed USDL Labor-Management Relations Training.

CREDENTIALS

BS cum laude, Sociology

Upper Iowa University

Invited Speaker

Multicultural Diversity Forum Iowa Mosaic Diversity Conference Iowa Assoc. of Dispute Resolution Conference

Education/Learning Disabilities Major

Iowa State University

Society for Human Resources Conference Lt. Governor's Conference on Diversity